Guide to Carmen Louise Cross papers 1945-1984
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Carmen Louise Cross papers
1945-1984
1970-1973
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 449
Cross, Carmen Louise, 1919-2014. creator.
2.5 linear feet of shelf space and 1 oversize box
(Carmen) C. Louise Cross (1919-2014) was a 1972 Constitutional Convention delegate from Dawson County, Montana. Cross served as chair of the Natural Resources and Agriculture Committee at the Convention—the only woman to chair an Article Committee. Due in large part to Cross’ efforts, Montana’s Bill of Rights contains a constitutionally protected right to a “clean and healthful environment in Montana for present and future generations.” The collection (1971-1974) consists primarily of correspondence to and from her constituents during the Convention, as well as subject files and clippings on issues important to her.
Biographical Note
(Carmen) C. Louise Jarussi was born on October 26, 1919, in Columbus, Montana, to Louis and Carmen Jarussi. Her parents immigrated from Rivisondoli, Italy, in 1907. After finishing high school in Red Lodge, Montana, Jarussi attended the University of Montana where she graduated with a bachelor’s degree in English and speech, with minors in music and French. On June 23, 1943, Jarussi married John Melvin Cross, whom she met during a speech tournament her senior year at UM. John Cross served in the European Theater during World War II, and when the war ended, the couple settled in Helena, Montana until 1952 when they relocated to Glendive. The couple had six children: Melvin, Gregory, Brian, Justin, Mark, and Catherine.
Cross was active in the American Association of University Women, and in local Democratic Party politics. In 1971 she ran for and was elected a delegate to the 1972 Montana Constitutional Convention. Her interest in the Convention stemmed from her concerns related to land reclamation and the environmental impact of strip mining in eastern Montana. Cross served as chair of the Natural Resources and Agriculture Committee at the Convention—the only woman to chair an Article Committee. Due in large part to Cross’ efforts, Montana’s Bill of Rights contains a constitutionally protected right to a “clean and healthful environment in Montana for present and future generations.” It also provides for land reclamation and water rights. The article was challenged in 1991, but the Montana Supreme Court upheld it.
After the Convention, Cross ran for a seat on the Dawson County Commission, but lost. She remained active politically locally, serving as an election judge and working to establish the Frontier Gateway Museum to preserve eastern Montana history. She was the museum’s first curator.
An ardent environmentalist until she died, Cross was a member of organizations such as the Audubon Society, National Wildlife Foundation, and Northern Plains Resource Council. In 1997, she advocated for the protection of Montana’s largest state park, Makoshika State Park from oil development.
On March 21, 2014, two months before her death, Cross and four other Constitutional Convention delegates, Wade Dahood, Jean Bowman, Michael McKeon and Arlyne Reichert, went to court challenging Supreme Court justice candidate Lawrence VanDyke’s eligibility to run, arguing he was ineligible to run under the constitutional requirement that requires an attorney to be admitted to the practice of law in Montana for 5 years prior to election.
Louise Cross died on May 16, 2014. Her husband, John, preceded her in death on January 25, 1980.
The (Carmen) C. Louise Cross papers are arranged in six series: correspondence (1971-1974), organizational records (1972), reports (1972), ephemera (1972), subject files (bulk 1970-1974), and news clippings (1971-1973). Subject files relate to environmental issues, particularly strip mining, and the Constitutional Convention make up the bulk of the collection. While some of the correspondence relates to Cross’ work on the Natural Resources and Agricultural Committee, much of it contains suggestions from constituents about other constitutional issues. Correspondence is arranged by subject, mostly relating to Cross’ work during the Constitutional Convention, and consists mainly of constituent concerns and suggestions. The organizational records series contains information about the Constitutional Convention that was authored by Cross and the other delegates. The reports and ephemera series each contain only a few items, and the clippings series contains mostly information about environmental issues related to coal mining.
In most cases the original order was retained as the creator appears to have arranged the correspondence, subject files and clippings by subject.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
The bulk of the print materials were separated to the Library. The photographs were transferred to the Photo Archives.
Several other collections about the 1972 Montana Constitutional Convention are held at the Montana Historical Society including: the Dorothy Eck papers(MC 448), Arlyne Reichert papers (MC 450),Montana Constitutional Convention Records (RS 22), and Montana Constitutional Convention Commission Records (RS 21).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Cross, Carmen Louise--Political activity.; Eck, Dorothy, 1924- --Political activity.; Graybill, Leo--Political activity.
Montana. Constitutional Convention (1971-1972)--History.; Montana. Constitutional Convention (1889)--History.; Montana. Constitutional Convention (1971-1972); Montana. Constitutional Convention (1971-1972). Natural Resources and Agriculture Committee.; Montana. Constitutional Convention (1971-1972)--Constituent communication.; Montana. Constitution Revision Commission.; Montana. Constitution Convention Commission.; American Association of University Women. Montana Division--History.
Local elections--Montana.; Constitutional conventions--Montana.; Constitutional history--Montana.; Women--Political activity--Montana.; Local government--Montana.; Women politicians--Montana--Glendive.; Conservation of natural resources.; Environmental policy--Montana.; Reclamation of land--Montana.; Watersheds.; Strip mining.; Coal mines and mining.
Montana--Politics and government--20th century.; Helena (Mont.); Glendive (Mont.); Colstrip (Mont.); Dawson County (Mont.)
Montana; Women
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence, 1971-1974
  - Citizen Suggestions, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Coal, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Constituent Correspondence, 1971-1972; This folder contains a letter from Jeannette Rankin to Georgia State Senate (Box-folder 1 / 3-4)
  - Land Reclamation, 1973 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Personal / Con Con related, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Ratification, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
- Organizational Records, 1972
  - Organization and Procedures, 1972 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Con Con Natural Resources Proposals, 1972 (Box-folder 2 / 1-2)
  - Committee Proposals, final drafts, 1972; Annotated by Cross. (Volume Volumes 1-2)
- Ephemera, 1972
  - Con Con Name Plate, Bumper stickers and other Con Con materials, 1972 (Box-folder 3/ 1)
- Reports, 1972
  - Con Con committee reports, 1972; Annotated by Cross. (Box-folder 3/ 2)
- Subject Files, 1945-1984
  - Coal, 1972 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - Coal: Strip Mining, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Con Con: Constitutional Revision Examples, 1972 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - Con Con: Constituent Suggestions, 1972 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Con Con: Organization, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Con Con: Orientation, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - Con Con: Ratification, 1972 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
  - Con Con: Seminar, 1972; This folder contains an address by Margery Brown. (Box-folder 3 / 10)
  - Con Con: Testimony, 1972; Testimony of constituents directed toward the Education and Public Lands Committee. (Box-folder 3 / 11)
  - Con Con: Testimony, 1970-1972; Testimony of constituents directed toward the Natural Resources and Agricultural Committee. (Box-folder 4 / 1-3)
  - Environmental Issues, 1972-1984 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
  - Montana Citizens for Constitutional Improvement, 1971 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
  - Montana Constitutional Convention Instructional Idea and Resource Filie, 1972 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
  - Northern Rockies Action Group, 1973 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
  - "Water, Water Rights (Yellowstone River)", 1945-1983 (Box-folder 4 / 8)
  - Water Use, 1973 (Box-folder 4 / 9)
- Clippings, 1969-1983
  - Coal / Coal Mining, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 5 / 1-3)
  - Coal: Bull Mountains, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
  - Coal: Colstrip, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
  - "Coal: Eastern Montana, Dawson County, Glendive", 1972-1973 (Box-folder 5 / 6)
  - Coal: Legislation, 1972-1983 (Box-folder 5 / 7)
  - Coal: Native American Concerns, 1973 (Box-folder 5 / 8)
  - "Coal: Sarpy Creek, Burlington Northern, Decker, Birney", 1973 (Box-folder 5 / 9)
  - Coal: Strip Mining, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 5 / 10)
  - Con Con: Support, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 5 / 11)
  - Strip Mining, 1973-1979 (Oversizebox Oversize Box 1)